I will persuade Ferrante
no alliance with Sixtus
ever benefits
the Pope's partners.
You seek an alliance
against Florence?
How may we be of service?
We will apply
unrelenting pressure
until Lorenzo surrenders.
You carry Giuliano's seed?
Yes, signora.
So you will remain with us.
Are we on the right course?
We've been at sea for weeks.
That, together with this device,
enabled me to estimate
the length of our voyage.
If you're wrong, we die at sea.
We will not die at sea.
What are you teaching the boy?
How to survive when grace fails.
This ship will sink
without Da Vinci at the helm.
Storm on the way, Your Grace.
Could push us into the rocks.
Let me out, please!
(THUNDER CRASHES)
♪ DaVinci's Demons S02E05 The Sun and the Moon ♪
♪ Original Air Date on April 19, 2014 ♪
== sync, corrected
by elderman == @elder_man
(MUSIC)
Out you get.
Dry land.
Count Riario didn't pray
to his God hard enough.
This is not how I saw us
finding your New World.
The light here is different.
The rock striations,
the lush vegetation.
We need food, Leo.
It's remarkable.
This could be the gateway
to extraordinary things.
That's the figurehead
of the Basilisk.
One sailor to another.
No one survived this wreck.
ZOROASTER: We can't
write them off as dead.
Parts of the Basilisk
made it to the shore,
maybe survivors did as well.
If Riario survived, he'll have
weeks of advantage on us.
And he'll have taken
Nico with him.
(HISSES, HE GASPS)
I'll stay aboard with Captain
and chart these shores.
There's more money in making a map
to treasure than in searching for it.
Amerigo, we will return to this
shore in three months.
Do you swear to be
here for us then?
And if your motley assemblage
doesn't come back,
I'm to wait here on this
beach, cock in hand?
It's the perfect place
to tan your tiny prick.
If we don't return
by then, sail without us.
I'll mourn you...
as I'm celebrated
for discovering this land.
Of course you'll take the credit,
you buzzard's canker sore.
Bye-bye.
Maybe I will.
Maybe I'll name this whole
fucking place after myself!
Vespuccia!
(FIGHT TAKING PLACE)
Urgh! Argh!
And I used to love
visiting Naples.
A word, please, Officer.
Shut it, shit-slinger, I'm
trying to take a head count.
All the while we've been here,
we've not been given a chance
to state our case.
What case? Aren't you
the two they found burying bodies
with that chest of gold?
It was our gold, we acted
in our own defense.
Of course you did!
We are emissaries from Milan
with a vital message from Ludovico
Sforza for his sister Ippolita.
Duke Alfonso's wife?
Two paupers like yourselves
don't come bearing nothing
but cock rash.
We rode incognito
to elude bandits.
Now, here's something
you should see.
Didn't they search
you on the way in?
Inform the Duchess that we are here
on urgent business.
My name is Gallus and this
is my companion Daphnis.
The Duchess will know
who we are.
They made us disrobe.
Where exactly were
you hiding that?
Medici trade secret.
VANESSA: I miss
the city, maestro.
This palace lacks
Florence's vitality.
It feels an eternity I've been trapped
in this stale place.
Stale?
When this home was constructed,
Cosimo employed Michelozzo
to design unique flourishes -
hidden passages, spy
holes, coded messages.
For instance...
if you stand in that corner
I'll show you
one of my favorites.
So this Benedetto,
what exactly does he do
in your workshop,
other than look handsome?
He's a framer
for one of my latest commissions.
And you find no
other uses for him?
Now... listen.
(CLICKS FINGERS)
BENEDETTO: Vanessa, can we talk
Andrea into shaving that beard?
It bristles against my skin.
I heard him
as though he was next to me!
How is this possible?
It's called a whisper corridor.
The circular construction allows
sound to travel perfectly,
from one precise
location to another.
Walls that talk.
Amazing!
Signor Sassetti, I promised
the captain funds
for the hiring of more officers.
What gives you the right
to turn him away?
My title.
As general manager
of the Medici Bank,
it's solvency is my solemn duty.
I cannot approve
another loan to a government
which already holds
significant debts.
This is not a loan but
a simple withdrawal
of Medici family assets.
Another request I must deny.
You may not realize
that as your husband left for Naples,
he withdrew an enormous
sum from our coffers.
I must insist
all accounts suspended...
until debts
are reasonably repaid.
As I insist you resign.
A majority of the board must
approve executive hiring.
Or firing.
If Lorenzo were here...
But he's not, is he?
Instead, shortly
after losing his mistress,
he heads to Naples...
a land which, by staggering
coincidence,
is home to his first love,
Ippolita Sforza,
the Duchess of Calabria.
In such an absence,
you cannot blame us for doing
what we think best.
(HISSES)
(INSECTS BUZZING)
Fuck.
It really is a new world.
I haven't had this much fluid sucked
out of me since that girl in Beretola.
In all my years as a painter,
I've never seen
a vermillion like this.
Really?
Leo, not bothered by the howling
beasts in the trees
but a new color? Yes,
that gives you pause.
Prick.
(EXHALES)
(GRUNTS)
Da Vinci?
Look at the finishing of this.
It's pure gold.
Shit.
We are on track.
But the people here,
they just leave out gold
for the taking.
What are you doing? We haven't
been paid since Genoa.
I promise you payment in abundance
on our return to Florence.
But not if you disturb
what is clearly a sacred idol.
(SPEAKS IN QUECHUA)
Hey, hey.
We're friends. Friends.
Keep still.
We're visitors.
We seek men...
like ourselves.
Primitive. He may
think the same of us.
Wait, wait! Wait!
Brilliant! That's brilliant.
You raise weapons,
he tells his people,
and we've made an enemy
before we've even spoken a word.
Thank you...
T-Thank you so much
for your steady nerve!
We press on.
But keep your blades ready
for the fight that you
may have handed us.
(SIGHS)
Shit.
You lied about us being
Milanese emissaries.
They're most likely choosing
the piazza to display our corpses.
Lorenzo?
Lorenzo! Ippolita.
Lucifer himself would call you
a holy fool for coming here.
I had no other choice.
Gallus and Daphnis?
The names of the lovers
in Eclogue Ten.
I knew you would remember.
How could I forget?
On the banks of the River Po,
reading all Virgil's verses.
We rarely finished.
And to think I lost you...
to that Roman woman
and the Orsini name.
Clarice... has her virtues.
Ah. Do you read poetry together?
As we speak,
she watches over my Republic
as your husband brandishes
arms against it.
I tried.
I pleaded for him not
to move against you.
After the attack
on your family...
Poor Giuliano.
I cannot bear
the thought of Alfonso
bringing more death to Florence.
Your husband is a warrior.
He takes up weapons
as automatically
as a child handles a plaything.
That is why we are here, Your
Grace, to speak with King Ferrante.
My father-in-law
will not listen.
He is...
Just like a Florentine,
to enter from the back door.
Alfonso.
Lorenzo has come to meet
with your father.
I had hoped to act
as an intermediary.
Of course.
That must be why you came
here without a royal escort.
It wasn't her idea, Alfonso.
I called upon her to...
come to me alone.
You dare enter
Naples unannounced
and meet with my wife in secret?
Alfonso, I... Duke Alfonso.
I...implore you...
let me sit with your father
and end this pointless war.
Of course.
Of course I will take
you to my father.
We are...
civilized heads of state.
Are we not?
Trouble sleeping?
I'm at your mercy, my lady.
I only seek a discussion
away from prying ears.
And what if someone
saw you enter?
I took precautions.
I would never risk your dignity.
Henbane, bark of mandrake
and juice of lettuce.
An ineffective potion
against the restless sleep of leadership.
But a necessary one.
Other leaders of this
family have found relief
in distractions of the flesh.
I need no schooling
in my husband's habits.
What do you want?
To offer assistance
with Portinari and Sassetti.
Their scheming is obvious.
I need no help with greedy
jackals, I grew up in Rome.
I wish to make sure they
take no advantage
of what they perceive as weakness.
They were trained by my father.
Cosimo demanded a certain
ruthlessness in those he employed.
And I will gladly
respond in kind.
Consider their perspective.
They believe the bank weak
with a woman at it's head,
akin to how my father denied
me a place in it's management.
You were illegitimate.
A bastard...
with an unsuitable complexion.
Almost as bad as being a woman.
So you'd like an alliance...
a seat on the Medici Bank
board after all these years.
Giuliano's seat remains vacant.
You're as clever
as you are beautiful.
Don't waste your time
flattering me.
Appoint me...
and I vote with you
on all matters.
A bastard and a woman.
Quite the partnership.
Good night, signor.
(GRUNTS)
Shit.
This is the work
of civilization.
Ah, fuck!
Normally, I like things
hot and wet.
We're on the right path.
We should make camp.
Yeah, why not?
(TWIG SNAPS, BIRDS CRY)
(MAN SHOUTS IN QUECHUA)
(SHOUTING)
Whoa.
They're just...
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
Look.
Look, these symbols.
Do you see?
It's the same.
Friends.
In the name of the Father,
Son and Holy Ghost, amen.
Where is he?
(DOOR OPENING)
Carlo.
I must commend your powers
of persuasion.
Clarice has officially nominated you
to fill Giuliano's seat on the board.
As I assured you she would.
This maneuver does nothing
to solve our problem.
Clarice still holds over half
the board in her palm.
That will change with time
and persistence.
The time to act is now.
Lorenzo and Clarice still
hold the favor of the people.
And what if we replaced her
with someone we could
sell as Lorenzo's choice?
With the same name.
Our plan is my succession.
Your plan is taking too long.
For your creditors... Enough.
What is your proposition?
This letter, penned by King
Ferdinand of Aragon himself,
details, at my suggestion,
his intention to default
on all loans from the Medici Bank
unless Clarice is removed
from leadership.
Spain is our largest account.
How does this aid our 'cause?
I negotiated a steady
repayment schedule...
with a slight reduction
in interest,
once Carlo takes
control of the bank.
Is this true?
A Medici Bank run by a Medici.
But without the embarrassment
of a woman at it's head.
Even Signor Rinaldi has
indicated he will vote with us.
Albini teeters,
but can be swayed.
Be sure to emphasize
Carlo's role in this.
It will ensure their support.
Clarice will be
out of the picture soon enough.
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
Leo, they're going
to fucking kill us.
No.
They've fed us,
they've transported us for Miles.
They've got something
else in mind.
ZOROASTER: Yeah, being
their next meal.
This is an advanced people, Zo.
Take their language.
Leo, please tell me you're
trying to find a way to escape,
not just decipher
their gibberish.
Ssh.
Listen. Every sound they make is a key
to the puzzle of their tongue.
The leader keeps referring
to himself as "noqa" for "I"
and "noqanchik"
for "us as a group".
Obviously. Yeah.
I've repeatedly heard the word
"puriy" and "purinchik"
to describe an action
that's occurred throughout the time
that we've been with them.
It translates as "walk"
and "we walk".
(SHOUTS IN QUECHUA)
Making friends, are we?
That word, "yawar".
They used it when they fed us
the llama milk mixed with blood.
Please mean milk.
Uh... no, it suggests we may be
marching to our death after all.
Oh.
I do not claim to be
a wine cognoscente,
an amateur oenophile, perhaps.
But this Frescobaldi -
a first-rate Tuscan chianti.
Very popular amongst the Florentine
aristocracy.
A talented winemaker indeed.
Shame that he perished
along with his family
when my soldiers
torched his vineyard.
Al.
All that was salvaged
from the estate
are the bottles now
in my possession.
We also thank you for the new
garments, Duke Alfonso.
Formal delegates from Florence
must look the part.
(CHUCKLES)
Though I question why Lorenzo
brought along an antique
and not a more
formidable companion.
Piero Da Vinci
is my personal notary.
And one of my most trusted
counselors.
Da Vinci? Kin to Leonardo?
Indeed.
He is the um...
proud father
of the celebrated artist.
And sodomite. Never convicted.
(CHUCKLES)
I've met the man. I read
a different verdict.
Leonardo works
for Florence from afar.
Demean him at your peril.
Will the King be joining us?
I feel a monarch of his years will bring
invaluable wisdom to this table.
(HORSE WHINNIES)
Yes, indeed.
I will do whatever it takes
to resolve our conflict.
Father will be pleased
to hear that.
He so enjoys it when his captives
are willing to play along.
Oh!
What have you done?
Precisely what you asked.
The King is looking
forward to seeing you.
(LAUGHS)
Damn them!
Or rather, damn myself,
as I stand the dupe in all this.
Signora...
this knowledge provides
an opportunity
to counter their schemes.
I only wish it did.
Carlo's confirmation
to the board is but a formality.
If I raise an objection now,
it'll further
weaken my position,
given that I nominated
Carlo myself.
I cannot believe I was so
easily fooled by him.
Perhaps you were not.
Well, you heard the whispers.
Sassetti only spoke of using
Carlo's name in their scheme.
There's a chance Carlo
himself is unaware.
Unlikely.
The Pazzis proved the seduction
of power is intoxicating.
He doesn't care about power.
He's here because of his father.
How do you know this?
She asked me to present
all this to you.
She was afraid...
Why, what have you heard?
The servants trust Carlo.
They say he was always a Medici,
despite being wronged by those
who scorned his lineage.
He was his father's favorite.
Some believe, if there's anyone
Cosimo shared his secrets with,
it was Carlo.
(GUARD SHOUTS IN QUECHUA)
The sickness will pass once
we get used to the altitude.
Or we can just launch
ourselves over the edge here.
Don't try it while you're
bound to me!
So are we gonna let
these savages kill us?
The alternatives are rather
limited just now.
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
They're distracted by news
from that messenger.
I could be free from the pole
with a couple of tugs.
Then what? We try and run
still bound to these poles?
Have you anything better?
We have to go out fighting.
Now is not the time!
And later, when we're brought
before some crag-faced cannibal?
Look at where listening
to you has brought us.
Aaargh!
(GRUNTS)
(SHOUTS COMMAND)
Tell her I'll be
happy to service her
in any number of ways
to save the rest of you.
I'm willing to make
that sacrifice.
Our destination.
The town made of stone.
Just as the Abyssinian said.
I take back what I said
about savages.
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
It is unanimous.
Carlo de Medici,
welcome to the governing
board of the Medici Bank.
I shall strive to satisfy
your faith in me.
Signors...
have we any other business?
Unfortunately, there is an issue
of grave importance.
I have recently had rd
from King Ferdinand
of his intention to default
payment on all loans
unless we remove Clarice Orsini
as head of this institution
for her sins
against the Holy Church.
Clearly, I will not capitulate
to the blackmail of a creditor.
A true leader would take
whatever steps necessary
to ensure our business
sees another day, month...
If this is your attempt at requesting
my resignation, rethink.
Without a vote of this
board, it will not happen.
Then you leave us no choice.
Signors, let us answer
the call for new leadership.
A majority of seven is required.
Carlo, how will you vote?
As a man of faith,
I respect a commitment
to the Holy Church.
And supporting him is wise
if that's what forces Ferdinand's decision.
But it is not.
I vote with Clarice Orsini.
This letter details
the back-room deal
between King Ferdinand
and Signor Portinari,
in which favorable interest
rates were offered
in direct exchange
for the King's threat of default.
I charge this letter not
only as malfeasance
but also treason.
Guards, remove this well-fed
Judas to the Bargello.
This is outrageous!
This melanzana deceived us!
I'll... get... you...
back... for this!
Signors, today each of you have
made your loyalties clear.
Now I must consider what to do
with those no longer
supporting my leadership.
Signor de Medici, I wonder,
do you have any suggestions?
Perhaps this board
has grown too large.
We can do more with less.
Unless some members would be
willing to relinquish
a portion of their sizeable
salaries for the good of Florence?
Excellent.
I trust the details
are secure in your hands.
(RETCHES)
The sickness
to your stomach will pass.
(COUGHS)
My alchemists continually
tinker with their recipe
for oil of vitriol.
They never get it right.
When I was a young man,
a Chinese delegation
came to Italy,
bearing many treasures.
But their most precious gift
was teaching their art
of preserving human bodies.
The use of antimony salts
in embalming fluid.
Inspired!
Where is Piero?
Intact...
for the time being.
The human body always reminds
me of our Italian peninsula.
Such a complex assembly
of delicate parts,
each one with a purpose.
Yet every now and then...
one brings down the others.
For the rest
of the organism to thrive,
a steady and unwavering hand
is called upon to remove...
the infected piece.
King Ferrante...
you may see Florence
as a disease.
But if you'll allow me
to speak on her behalf...
What's more to say?
The Holy Father himself
decreed your city...
unbecoming in the eyes
of the Lord.
Pope Sixtus has overreached,
as he has in the past.
The Duke of Milan
was murdered at his behest.
Even my own brother, Giuliano,
slaughtered in a house of worship
on holy Easter Sunday.
Popes come and go.
I choose my alliances for the safety
and glory of my own kingdom.
Then side with Florence!
You seek to curb
Ottoman incursions.
You fear the French will renew
their claims to Naples.
I fear no one.
Not that dandy French king.
Or an Ottoman infidel
eyeing our shores.
You speak of fear?
I will show you fear.
(DISTANT CHANTING AND DRUMS BEATING)
(CHANTING INTENSIFIES)
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
He looks fancy.
(CHANTING)
(CROWD GASPS)
Whatever's about to happen...
she's not happy about it.
Yeah. That makes two of us.
(CROWD CHANTING)
Kaliari!
Kaliari.
What am I supposed to do?
"Kaliari".
I think they want us to choose.
I saw this in Mali.
It's a ritual to determine
your value to the tribe.
You must choose an item
to identify your place
among them.
PRIEST: Kaliari!
Then I choose to be a warrior!
Amongst warriors!
(CROWD CHEERS)
I am pleased you
honored our accord.
Why would I do otherwise?
Because you broke the deal
you made with Portinari
and Sassetti.
So I cannot help wonder when
your word means something.
I tested them to lure them out.
But I could not be bound
to any vow that might
harm your interests.
Well, I...
I'm impressed.
Thank you.
You take vows very seriously.
As do I.
But when others do not
honor their promises,
neither should you feel bound
to anything but your own interests.
Duly noted.
I will not discuss the matter
unless you bring it up.
I await your pleasure.
(GROANS)
Welcome to my black museum.
Every piece here was prepared
and arranged by my own hands.
Their faces bear the mark
of their final moment on our earth.
Here it is on display.
Fear - for my amusement.
Why would you do such a thing?
Every piece here became part
of my collection by their own hand.
Each of them was in the position
you are now in,
Lorenzo.
Held against his will by a mad
king?
I am a king, yes.
All the same, I rule
by divine right.
So all must earn
a seat at my table.
How?
Call it a game.
You are a hunter, are you not?
My brother more than me.
My game requires
exceptional skill.
What do you say?
Does Florence have
a champion in you?
Or are you just
another pretender?
I will accept any sick
measure you cast my way.
Wonderful.
I await your attempt
to demonstrate true merit.
Or die like the rest.
What choice?
Da Vinci?
You're cleverer than I am.
I don't know. What?
I don't know, I don't know.
Perhaps if I had more time.
Then like our Lord... Come on!
I drink from his chalice.
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
(CHEERING)
At least there's only one choice left.
We may get out alive.
No, that can't be all there is.
They're too advanced for that.
The thin air's gotten to you.
We're gonna be alright.
There's got to be more to it
than a process of elimination, Zo.
Fuck, I'm missing something!
Then fucking figure it out!
He wants us dead.
You need us to succeed.
Of course.
The only time an exotic
beauty chooses me over you,
it's the death-dealing one.
Pai. Pai, good.
There's nothing advanced
about these monsters.
They're just playing
with their fucking food.
(CROWD CHANTS)
Oh, fuck.
Oh, Jesus. Fuck...
(SHOUTS)
(CROWD GASPS)
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
Okay. Fuck.
Are you sure about this?
What the fuck are you doing?
Kalsai.
(CROWD CHANTS)
Kalsai! Kalsai!
Life.
That's the answer they seek.
(SPEAKS QUECHUA)
Leonardo Da Vinci.
She knows my name.
She knows my name!
(GRUNTS)
Zo?
Nico!
You little pizzle! Nico!
Oh, it is so good to see you!
That shipwreck, I knew it'd take
more than that to sink him.
How did you survive?
Not everyone abandoned him.
Shitheel.
Let him.
Get up. Get up!
I tried to take your life, so...
I understand your desire
to do the same.
But today, we are united
by the hand of the divine.
No, Don't!
Out of my way, Nico,
he deserves every bit of this!
I can't let you.
After what he did?
Left me to drown, tortured you.
Why does this prick
deserve mercy?
If the Lord wanted him dead,
he would've taken him at sea.
What?
God spared us all.
That is a sign that we must join
together to achieve our goal.
Who the fuck is we? He's right.
It's us against them. No, no.
Count.
Artista.
(SPITS)
Our prayers for deliverance
have been answered.
Today, we are blessed.
This is blessed? Yes.
Yes, it is. I live by faith.
For weeks, we have been held
captive thousands of Miles
from home atop this Mountain
with no hope of escape, then...
he sends you.
But...
if we put our minds
to freedom, Da Vinci,
the wisdom of the Book
of Leaves will be ours.
The Book of Leaves...
is not meant for just you and I.
The Book of Leaves
will save us all.
RIARIO: You understand us.
He learns our tongue.
Is it so impossible
that I could speak yours?
It creates many questions.
I am Ima Kama,
High Priestess
of the Children of the Sun.
And I shall answer
all questions.
But only to you.
Why me?
Your face
is one I've seen before.
(DOOR CLANGS)
(MOANS IN ECSTASY)
Christ, I needed that!
These markings tell
the story of my people.
We have no need to travel
the seas as you do.
And yet, somehow, you learned
to speak our language.
You are not the first
of your kind to arrive.
They came here when
I was just a little girl.
We called them the Sun
and the Moon.
Who are they?
The man was dark as night,
with images etched
into his skin.
The Abyssinian.
He aided me on my journey
to this place.
And the woman?
Bright and warm as the sun.
She saved me
from being sacrificed.
She used her knowledge
to heal my wounds.
And set me on the path
to High Priestess.
The day she left here,
she told me you
would follow in her path.
It is her face I see
in yours, Leonardo.
My mother.
She was here.
Caterina lived among us
for many days and nights.
And she taught me your tongue.
She spoke of her vow
to see you again
once her task was done.
She came for the Book of Leaves.
Your mother and the Book
of Leaves saved my life.
It's real.
It's real! It's real!
== sync, corrected
by elderman == @elder_man
(MUSIC)
http://subscene.com/u/659433
Improved by: @Ivandrofly